what are your most frustrating trading
moments if you're anything like me it
won't take you long to answer there are
certain trades that just seem to linger
in your memory like a bad taste just as
vividly as your biggest successes and
the one that hauns me the most was from
back in 2014 about 10 years ago now I
was holding a short trade on the Euro
decent position size I had over 30 Lots
open the technicals gave me a solid
entry around 138 and the fundamentals
were suggesting that we could reach at
least 120 so potentially a huge move but
I was worried that if we broke 140 it
would lead to a surge of momentum and I
didn't want to be on the wrong side of
that you know how it tends to be around
these sort of major levels so that's
where I CT my risk just below 140 and
time passed and the price didn't really
do much to start with not this bearish
meltdown that I was hoping for but then
price did start moving it started
creeping higher not what I wanted it to
do and eventually a sudden jolt just
sent it driving towards 140 and took me
out of the trade but the thing is the
price didn't quite reach 140 it got
above
1399 something and then started falling
like a cannonball and in the following
months it not only reached 120 which is
what I was expecting but it dropped all
the way below 105 over 30 Lots at 138
entry I'm sure you can imagine that
trade felt like a double loss there was
the real capital I lost on the trade
when it hit my stop loss and then the
missed profits which would have been
anywhere between 500,000 and a million
depending on where I exited and I still
think about it to this day it haunts me
10 years later but I'm not the only one
whenever I meet up with other Traders
the conversation always finds its way to
our favorite trades and the ones that
got away and there are two main
categories of those frustrating trades
there are the missed entries that would
have been huge if you took them and then
the ones that you exited at the wrong
time either a great profit that you held
too long until it disappeared into dust
or the ones that you exited too early
just like my Euro gut rener and usually
it's due to a mistake that you've made
if it wasn't it probably wouldn't bother
you as much as it does what makes them
so frustrating is that you should have
known better this is Simon Ramo a
scientist who's known as the father of
the intercontinental ballistic missile
alongside writing about things like
microwaves in space strangely he decided
to write several books on tennis and he
made an important observation he said in
expert tennis about 80% of the points
are won in amateur tennis about 80% of
the points are lost in other words
professional tennis is a Winner's game
the final outcome is determined by the
activities of the winner and amateur
tennis is a losers game the final
outcome is determined by the activities
of the loser so if you're an amateur and
you're playing against another amateur
and you want to win then rather than
trying to play winning shots the most
successful strategy is to focus on
making fewer mistakes and funnily enough
trading at an early stage is quite
similar you see early in your career
after you've learned the foundations
like the necessary skills and Concepts
the biggest impact on your trading
performance won't be your moments of
Genius instead the biggest impact will
come from your mistakes and I'm not
talking about times when the problem is
a lack of knowledge or a lack of skill
those wouldn't really be mistakes
instead most Traders lose money overall
because they make mistakes that they
know they shouldn't be making so why do
you make these sorts of mistakes if you
should know better well there are three
key reasons firstly there are really
common skill related problems that most
Traders aren't even aware that they have
and these have a major impact on your
trading psychology which then increases
the chance of a range of different
mistakes happening and I explained this
in an earlier video which you can click
up here to watch and usually by
resolving these skill issues you will
reduce the psychological problems and
this will stop you from making those
sorts of mistakes secondly we have the
emotional aspects that are not related
to how you approach the skill as the
trading psychologist Denise sha says b
ikb but I know better trades set up
feeling and emotional contexts and also
emerge from conscious and unconscious
emotional contexts of self-recrimination
just catching yourself in those and the
feelings surrounding them will impact
your bottom line in a positive way
knowing the feeling cluster radiating in
your psychological environment gives you
the chance to evaluate whether it
signals a risk to be managed or an
opportunity to take advantage of so in
other words you need to track when those
mistakes are happening and take note of
the feelings that emerg during that time
and by doing that you can recognize
those situations in future in real time
and evaluate the situation more
correctly this is something I'll explain
a bit more in a separate video but the
third reason is by far the most
troubling because it can happen
regardless of how experienced you are or
how great your trading usually is as
Donald Rumsfeld famously said there are
known knowns there are things we know we
know we also know there are known
unknowns that is to say we know there
are some things we do not know but there
are also unknown unknowns the ones we
don't know we don't know it's those
bloody unknown unknowns so many of our
mistakes are due to cognitive biases and
mental blind spots we're not even aware
that we're making these mistakes we
don't know that we're doing something
wrong and they affect all of us research
by Daniel Carman and other psychologists
has revealed that we all have these
blind spots and these biases regardless
of our level of intelligence or IQ or
anything else here's one of the tests
that they use Jack is looking at an but
an is looking at George Jack is married
but George is not is a married person
looking at an unmarried person a yes B
no or C cannot be determined so have a
think about it and pause the video if
you're not ready for the answer yet okay
so most people answer C cannot be
determined here's another question for
you a bat and a ball cost $110 cents in
total the bat cost $1 more than the ball
how much does the ball cost okay again
pause the video if you don't want the
answer yet have a think about it so in
this case most people answer that the
ball cost 10 cents is that the same as
what you got even if you test the most
intelligent people in the population the
majority will give those answers that I
just mentioned but the thing is both of
those answers are wrong for the first
question the answer is a yes and for the
second question the answer is 5 cents
the reason most people answer those
questions wrong is because of the mental
blind spots that we have and most people
won't notice until after the answer is
revealed and they start trying to figure
out why that's the right answer and
Suddenly It's so obvious otherwise they
wouldn't have thought twice about it and
obviously this activity is meaningless
but think about how many other areas of
your life or you're trading this same
thing's happening and you're making a
mistake and not realizing until maybe
it's revealed to you and this brings me
on to an important cavat the
psychologist Keith stanovich and his
team discovered one advantage that
intelligent people have if you explain
how they might go wrong before they
answer the question they perform a huge
amount better so for example for the
first question there they're simply told
that they need to use disjunctive
reasoning and that leads to them
performing much better getting the right
answer so this gives us an important
Insight we don't necessarily need to
know the specific mistakes that we're
likely to make we just need to
anticipate the ways we might go wrong
that lead to the mistakes the incorrect
ways of thinking that we need to avoid
or the correct ways of thinking that we
might neglect now that might sound
simple on face value but if you try it
you'll quickly realize that it's one of
of these things that's easier said than
done but there are strategies that you
can use and to help you with that here
are three things that I've found to be
the most effective so let's start with
this one every Trader is told they
should keep a trading journal and to be
fair I think most Traders do for a while
they'll try and give it a go but very
few Traders manage to stick with their
journal and use it effectively over the
longer term even people that keep a
trading journal tends just wri in it
after a trade or at the end of a day or
week but then don't come back to it and
use the information that's in there but
I believe that a trading journal is the
most underrated and underutilized tool
for improving your trading by keeping a
trading journal you can identify the
mistakes that you're commonly making and
then find ways to anticipate them better
in future like you might create
checklists to help you overcome problem
areas or give yourself reminders or
alerts before entering a trade to point
out where you might go wrong and those
are just the obvious things but the
benefit of a trading journal for
avoiding mistakes goes much deeper than
that you see journaling is a form of
self-reflection and self-reflection has
been proven to be an extremely effective
way to improve decision- making and
problem solving as I mentioned earlier
we all suffer from cognitive biases
mental blind spots and other cognitive
errors and research has linked
self-reflection with a reduction in
these common biases and errors in fact
it can even lead to neurological changes
taking place in your brain that will
lead to you being more effective with
your decision- making in future the key
to this is to be as detailed and
introspective as possible don't just
take a few short notes about the trade
instead explain exactly what you were
thinking why you took the action or made
the choices that you did how were you
feeling at the time what could or should
you have done differently and if you're
not sure where to start with the trading
journal or you want to see how you could
do it better if you're already keeping
one check out the link in the
description box down below to the free
guide that we put together for you it
will walk you through exactly what you
to include in your Journal how to
structure it and all of the benefits of
each section and this is how I keep a
trading journal so if you want to
imitate how I do mine that's the link
you need to follow and you don't have to
just limit this to your trading
decisions in your day-to-day life you
could also make use of a decision
Journal this is what Daniel Carman has
praised as being the single best thing
someone could do in the markets to
improve their performance he says go
down to a local drugstore and buy a very
cheap notebook and start keeping track
of your decision decisions and the
specific idea is whenever you're making
a consequential decision something going
in or out of the portfolio just take a
moment to think write down what you
expect to happen why you expect it to
happen and then actually and this is
optional but probably a good idea is
write down how you feel about the
situation both physically and even
emotionally just how do you feel I feel
tired I feel good or this stock is
really draining me whatever you think
the key to doing this is that it
prevents something something called
hindsight bias which is no matter what
happens in the world we tend to look
back on our decision- making process and
we tilt it in a way that looks more
favorable to us so we have this bias to
explain what has happened okay next up
we have prospective hindsight this is
also sometimes known as a premortem
analysis in fact I prefer that term and
it's basically a cognitive strategy
where you assess all the potential
outcomes all the possible risks and
failures before taking a decision or an
action and this is a great way to
anticipate where you might go wrong and
then prime your brain to avoid those
things as well as having a bit of a plan
for it so think about a postmortem
analysis this is where you analyze a
situation after it's happened and try to
learn from it so with a premortem
analysis you're basically trying to do
this but before the event has taken
place you're Imagining the event has
already happened it's ended with a
negative outcome and then brainstorming
all the possible reasons for it turning
out so badly so basically rather than
asking yourself what went wrong you're
actually asking yourself what could go
wrong and you're then running through
all the potential issues that you might
not have considered otherwise you're
encouraging yourself to be pessimistic
and to think through all of the
potential catastrophes you know one of
the challenges that we face as Traders
is our own personal biases which we can
simplify as being optimism or pessimism
in particular situations and these
biases are often referred to as internal
context because they shape the way that
we perceive the world around us and we
all have slightly different internal
context and therefore we'll perceive
things in slightly different ways but
this can also lead us to miss Vital
Information or think of important things
as being inconsequential so prospective
hindsight helps us to set aside those
biases and examine potential risks much
more objectively all right on to the
third one so a few years ago someone
left a comment on one of our YouTube
videos and they were complaining that in
those videos around that time I was
explaining what not to do in the markets
but they didn't want that they wanted to
be told exactly what they should do and
you'll see this throughout the online
trading Community people will watch
videos of other people explaining their
secret Source the specific rules and
strategies that they use to succeed and
then they want to try and implement it
as well but if you're like me and you're
skeptical about most of these successes
that you see online you might not see
much value in listening to someone
else's advice about what you should do
but on the other hand these people are
far less likely to be lying about their
mistakes and failures and that's where I
believe the value is as Charlie manga
famously said all I want to know is
where I'm going to die so I'll never go
there this is the premise behind the
inversion Market model which we
discussed in a previous video and you
can click up there to watch it if you do
follow the previous tips that I gave you
and journal your decisions with more
detail you can learn from your own
mistakes but most Traders miss out on
learning from the mistakes of others and
learning from other people's mistakes
has been shown through research to be
one of the best ways to make even fewer
mistakes yourself and become a best
decision maker that's part of the reason
that the duo Community is so powerful
because it gives people a chance to
learn from other people's mistakes and
successes as well I mean just think back
to the Insight that we gained from
earlier when faced with a problem to
solve intelligent people perform a huge
amount better when they're told the ways
that other people tend to go wrong so if
you analyze other people's mistakes it
can help you to anticipate and avoid
those mistakes yourself so next time
you're watching a guru online maybe
spend more time breaking down the things
they did wrong and learn from those
instead but if you want my opinion
there's one major mistake that I see
almost all Traders making and solving
just this one mistake could already get
your trading on the right track and I
explained it all in this video here
which you should watch next thanks for
watching